Finding Aid for the Barbara and Willard Morgan photographs and papers LSC.2278
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 9: Barbara Morgan photographic material, 1920s-2000s; Negative numbers are written on many of the photographic prints and contact prints. Some prints are signed, stamped, or have labels crediting Barbara Morgan. Many unmounted prints have notations on the back, such as numbers or the lowerc
  - Subseries 9.8: Negatives and contact prints, 1920s-1970s, undated
    This subseries includes negatives and contact prints related to all of Barbara Morgan's creative and personal photographic works. There are also negatives and contact prints of photographs taken by both Barbara and Willard Morgan, including their collaborative projects such as the Barnes Foundation and other art documentation, their travels in the Southwest, family trips, and friends and family, including genealogical photography. Also included are negatives and contact prints of photographs by Willard Morgan of Los Angeles architecture, E. Leitz and Leica projects, photographs of Barbara and Willard taken by each other and by other photographers, including Ansel Adams, and copy photographs of other photographers' works, including Edward Weston.
    The raw images of photographic sessions and projects are included as well as many of the final prints developed by Barbara Morgan.
    Files of negatives, contact prints and sheets are also located within series and subseries related to particular works and projects throughout the collection.
    Negatives and contact prints are mostly separated, but some of the boxes include both.
    Most of the negatives and contact prints are marked with negative numbers assigned by Barbara Morgan.
    Negative numbers in the inventories and photo date books correlate with those that are written on negatives, prints and contact sheets throughout the collection. The inventories (box 43, folder 16) and photo date books (Box 44, folder 12; and Box 45, folders 1 and 2) also provide an overview of Morgan's photography throughout her career.
    PDFs of the original handwritten inventories and photo date books are attached:
    (*)The original handwritten inventories are housed in Box 43, folder 16. Photograph date books are housed in Box 44, folder 12; and Box 45, folder 1 and 2.
    The photo date books in boxes 44 and 45 also provide an overview and inventory of Morgan's photography throughout her career.
    This subseries contains the bulk of the Morgans' files of integrated contact prints and negatives (5 x 7 and 4 x 5 formats and roll film).
    For Morgan's photography projects such as books and photography for college campuses and schools see Series 4: Barbara Morgan photographic projects.
    The subseries is arranged in three categories--5 x 7 and smaller, 4 x 5 and smaller, and roll film--maintaining the original sequential order of the materials in the following boxes:
    5 x 7 and smaller: Boxes 422-430; 537; 545-556; 558-560
    4 x 5 and smaller: Boxes 290-305; 433-435; 454-465; 529-536; 538-544; 556-557; 561-563; 607-608
    Roll film: Boxes 214; 430-431; 556-557; 564-569; 607-608
    Separated Materials
    Twenty-six boxes of nitrate negatives were removed from the collection and housed in two flammable safety cabinets. Nitrate negatives must be digitized in order to be available for access.
    Please contact Special Collections reference (AskLSC@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
    Subjects include:
    By Barbara Morgan: Art work, Dance, Sarah LawrenceTreetops, Summer's Children; New York City; Bennington Festival 1938; UCLA.
    By Willard Morgan: Los Angeles architecture; Neutra photography including Health House, architecture and Leica; Morgan Camera; Early Pomona and California; Family photographs; Southern California travels and events; photographs of Barbara Morgan; Undeveloped film and negatives.
    Collaborative: Southwest and Mexico; Family Photographs.
    Formats include: 35mm rolled film, and 5 x 7 inch and smaller negatives.
    8 boxes of acetate negatives, prints, and contact sheets were separated for treatment by UCLA Library Preservation Studios. Please contact Special Collections reference (AskLSC@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
    - Cut film (5 x 7 format and smaller), 1920s-1970s, undated
      - circa 1920s-1950s, undated, Negatives and contact prints (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 422, Folder 6)
        Collaborative projects by Barbara and Willard Morgan and family. Includes trips to the Southwest, and notes regarding Papago 1954. Also includes photographs of Barbara and Willard, pets and children.
      - circa 1920s-1940s, undated, Contact prints (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 423, Folders 1-6)
        Paul Doering; Beaumont and Nancy Newhall; Ansel Adams; children and Treetops; Ed Powell; Joseph Campbell; Hittite; Helen Morgan; Ruth (pregnant, nude) and Bill Mitchell; Kay Lauterer (pregnant, nude); Barbara and Willard Morgan family and children: Lexington Ave, Barbara in her studio NYC, Scarsdale; Experimental light and Rayograms; Nature: trees, corn leaf; Photomontage elements: city, nature, body parts; C. Sheeler and beech tree; Macy's window; and Dance including Martha Graham American Provincials, José Limón, Erick Hawkins, May O'Donnell photomontage at World's Fair, Celebration postcard, Weidman, Frank Bauman.
      - 1937, undated, Prints and contact prints (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 424, Folders 1-5)
        Martha Graham (solo and group) in Sarabande, Harlequinade, Celebration (different than Sixteen Dances), American Document (similar to Sixteen Dances), Primitive Mysteries, Chronicle, Frontier, Deaths and Entrances, Deep Song and Immediate Tragedy; Graham programs and Indian drum photographs in Sixteen Dances, a Graham music score; copy photographs by Barbara Morgan of early Martha Graham: baby, young woman portrait in black looking down, and Graham in Ruth St. Denis company: Tocsin, Fragilite, East Indian Poem, Javanese dance and unidentified (photographs by White Studio, Soichi Sunami, Ray Hulf, and unidentified); copy photographs of Graham Group in Indian Dance and Snake Dance; Barbara Morgan exhibit La Danza Moderna Norte Americana at MOMA 1945; Willard Morgan architecture and other photographs; Southwest: postcard of Barbara Morgan cooking at Canyon de Chelly campsite; and Halloween Scarsdale Window Painting 1937.
      - undated, Contact prints and negatives (5 x 7) (Box 425, Folders 1-6)
        Includes experimental and photomontage elements: body close-ups, city, light drawings/other "light": Sun moment, Dawn moment, Tree light, Samadhi (original negative); Macy's window; Junkyard Series/Tin can; Nature - plants/trees: Amaryllis, begonia, cactus, corn, Funkia, Sumach, plants in window, thorn, walnut (macro) Funkia leaf (solarized) birch trees, fog 1941, Charles Sheeler and beech tree, trees in snow, other trees; ice on window, snow weeds, snow shadows, snow fence, snowscapes.
        Also includes Martha Graham in Sarabande, Morgan family members: Willard Morgan, Helen Morgan, Douglas Morgan, Bill Mitchell, Lloyd's Head, and Willard and Barbara Morgan house in Scarsdale, New Jersey.
      - undated, Contact prints (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 426, Folders 1-5)
        Components of photomontage: Fossil, Spring on Madison Square; Portraits, family and friends: James Austin, Beaumont Newhall, Willard and Ansel Adams in studio, Berenice Abbott, Dr. Suzuki, Louis Horst, Shell; Summer's Children; New York; sand painting; experimental light; nature; Dance: Merce Cunningham Totem Ancestor; Hanya Holm in Dance of Introduction; Doris Humphrey in Exhibition Piece; Anna Sokolow and group in Facade; Charles Weidman in On My Mother's Side; Weidman, José Limón and Billy Archibald in Traditions; Nelle Fisher; Graham and Group; Pearl Primus; Martha Graham solos in Deep Song, American Provincials, American Document: Indian Ancestor, and Emancipation; and with Erick Hawkins in American Document Puritan Duet; photographs of objects and Frontier musical score shown in Sixteen Dances. This box also includes non-dance contact prints including fossil and other nature elements for experimental photography, New York City photographs, and portraits of Berenice Abbott and Louis Horst.
      - 1938-1939, undated, Contact prints (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 427, Folders 1-5)
        Martha Graham and Erick Hawkins solo and together in American Document: Now, Indian Ancestors, Every Soul is a Circus; Graham solos in War Theme, Columbiad, Ekstatis, Lamentation, Letter to the World (Kick), and Graham on bench; and other Graham with Hawkins; Graham Group in Deaths and Entrances, Every Soul is a Circus, Primitive Mysteries, and Graham dancers Nelle Fisher, Freida Flier and Marjorie Mazia in Modern Satyric.
      - 1937-1939, undated, Contact prints (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 428, Folders 1-6)
        Graham, Hawkins and Cunningham in Every Soul is a Circus, and Puritan Love Duet; Graham solo in Letter to the World (Swirl), Columbiad, American Document Indian Solo, Sarabande, and Immediate Tragedy (1937); Hawkins solo in American Document, and Hawkins with Douglas Morgan and others in studio shots for fun; May O'Donnell 1939 World's Fair photomontage; Charles Weidman and group in Traditions and unidentified dance; Hanya Holm in Dance of Introduction, Louis Horst at piano with dancers. Nature and Plants images: plants in windows Scarsdale, New York; plants copy camera (parts); Nature-animals: cats, toad, frog, chickens, feather, moth, rock formations, honeycomb, ocean wave breaking, odds and ends, Doug and the toad prince, stone metate, and stone walls; Photomontage/photogram components and experimental light; Portraits, family and friends: Berenice Abbott, Samuel Barber, John Butler, Cowdrey-Johnston 1947, Virginia Creed, Otto Doering, Lewis Hine, baby Lightgarn, Edward Powell, James Prestini, Adrian Siegal, and M. Werner.
      - 1938, undated, Contact prints (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 429, Folders 1-4)
        Dance: Martha Graham solo in Deep Song, Satyric Festival, Ekstatis, Indian Ancestor solo, Graham with Erick Hawkins in Every Soul is a Circus and Puritan Love Duet, and Graham with Merce Cunningham in Every Soul is a Circus. Also Cunningham solo, Eric Hawkins solo, Hanya Holm in Want Ads, Bill Bales and Sophie Maslow, José Limón, Doris Humphrey solo in With My Red Fires and with group in Square Dance for Moderns, Humphrey-Weidman group in Shakers, Anna Sokolow and group in Façade, negatives and contacts set aside for Deba Patnaik for his book Icons of Dance, and Pogo (Lloyd) Morgan in mask and costume, jumping.
        Friends and family: Coca, Gilbert, Herc and Barbara, photographic portraits of Barbara Morgan and Beaumont Newhall, and Elsa Schmid.
        Architecture: Barnsdall details, garage-rubble, gutters, highway, New York City building and street signs, shop fronts, nightclubs, theaters, wrecked buildings.
        Nature: leaves, trees, corn stalks, Hittite.
        People: Treetops and children.
        Also includes radiation, Darkroom of Lee Parsons New Rochelle, and European posters.
      - undated, Contact prints, copy negatives, and contact sheets (Box 430, Folders 1-2)
        2 folders of copy negatives of photographic prints and photomontages by John Heartfield - subject: WWII, Hitler, and Third Reich; 2 folders containing negative strips (removed) and prints of the Fresh Air Fund project, 1958; and 1 folder of 8 x 10 contact sheet proofs of the Fresh Air Fund project photographs.
      - undated, Negatives and contact prints (Box 537)
        Primarily negatives and some contact prints by Barbara and Willard Morgan. Includes Barnes Foundation, Southwest Museum, Chief Standing Bear, Scranton Pennsylvania lace mill, J.C. Matson piloting Stearman airplane, California Plains and Southwest: Trampas New Mexico, Arizona, Penetente, Grand Canyon. Also includes Kim Weber: Freudmeman Home and Lovich Dress Display Room in Los Angeles; J.R. Davidson: Hi-Hat Restaurant, Satyr Book Shop, Schillings Flowers, Hite-Bilicke Office, Presman; and Willard Morgan: Inter-American Visual Library proposal and letters, early Leica photographs, and Barth + Contax. Also includes photographs by Edward Weston.
      - circa 1920s-1954, undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 545, Folders 1-8)
        Grand Canyon, Mono Lake, Willard with Leica, Canyon de Chelly, Rito de los Frijoles, New Mexico, Kachina, Penitente Country, Rainbow Bridge and hiking to it, Barbara working in Southwest Museum, sand paintings, Snag Lake, Zuni paintings, Yoly Boly, Papago 1954, Prestini Column, NYC at night.
        Includes 1928 photograph by Willard Morgan of Barbara Morgan, sitting on a ledge, secured with rope, and with a large artists' tablet on her lap, painting the Grand Canyon.
      - undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 546, Folders 1-5)
        X-ray skull, Prestini portrait, New York City photographs: Chrysler building, streets, etc., trees, Lucy Doering speedlight, Hittite, Helen Morgan, pregnant--Ruth Mitchell and Kay Lauterer, Morgan family New York City and Scarsdale.
      - 1938-1975, undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 547, Folders 1-4)
        The Morgan home Scarsdale and family: cat Boots, Willard (Herc), Doug and animals, Barbara, Doug and Pogo archery, and horse barn.
        Also includes photomontage components, photograms, rayograms and light drawings.
      - 1933-1945, undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 548, Folders 1-5)
        Photomontage components, photograms, light drawings, and copy negatives by others including Moholy Nagy, John Heartfield, Ontwerd, Europa Magazine; Barbara Morgan photomontage lecture text; Barnes Foundation art works: Peruvian, Incan, Matisse mural; Barbara Morgan MOMA exhibition La Danza Moderna; and copy negatives of photographs by Moholy-Nagy and Edgerton.
      - 1926-1952, undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 549, Folders 1-6)
        Photomontages: Miss America, loyalist poster, What Are You Doing to Prevent This?; Barbara Morgan 1952 Summers Children exhibit at New York Public Library; photo techniques by Edgerton and Muybridge; Willard Morgan copy negatives; baseball; early Martha Graham and family including East Indian Poem, Javanese dance, Tocsin, and copy negatives of Indian Snake Dance, Young Martha Graham dancer. Also includes photographs of Mayan art.
      - 1933-1947, undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 550, Folders 1-7)
        Body close-ups: fist, knee, foot; New York City: Madison Square from Morgan Studio 1939 and other city photographs; Friends and family: portraits of Douglas and Willard Morgan including Doug's Head, Helen Morgan and Murray Elliott, pregnant Ruth Mitchell and Bill Mitchell, Dance: Martha Graham in Sarabande, Letter to the World (Swirl) and with Erick Hawkins; Light drawings including original Samadhi negatives; Junkyard series; Nature: corn, plants and trees including Charles Sheeler and beech tree, ice and snow.
      - 1939-1946, undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 551, Folders 1-6)
        Snow and ice; Morgan house and barn in Scarsdale; Photomontage components; Edward Weston shell.
        Dance: Merce Cunningham Totem Ancestor copy negative; Doris Humphrey in Exhibition Piece, Hanya Holm in Dance of Introduction; Anna Sokolow and Group in Facade; Charles Weidman, José Limón and Billy Archibald in On My Mother's Side and Traditions; 1939 Martha Graham dance props, instruments, programs and musical scores for Deep Song and Primitive Mysteries; Graham solos in American Document--Emancipation and Indian Ancestor, and with Erick Hawkins in Puritan Love Duet; and Louis Horst at piano.
      - 1935-1940, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 552, Folders 1-5)
        Dance: Graham in Columbiad, Deaths and Entrances, Ekstasis solo and with Erick Hawkins in studio photographs, American Document, Letter to the World, and Every Soul is a Circus; Graham Group in Primitive Mysteries, and Graham Group dancers Nelle Fisher, Frieda Flier, and Marjorie Mazie.
      - 1936-1947, undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 553, Folders 1-5)
        Plants in windows.
        Nature: animals and other--chicken, frog, cats, feather, lunar moth, rock formations, honeycomb, Doug and the Toad Prince.
        Photomontage and photogram components.
        Portraits and people: Berenice Abbott, Samuel Barber, John Butler, Mary Isabelle Cowdrey-Johnston 1947, Virginia Creed, Otto Doering, Lewis Hine, baby Lightgarn, Edward Powell, James Prestini, Adrian Siegal, M. Werner.
        Lake Treetops at night; science objects copy camera; Alpine quartz crystal; stone walls and gardens; and Madison Square from 1939 Morgan studio.
      - 1932-1942, undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) including color negatives of Graham, Humphrey and Hawkins (Box 554, Folders 1-4)
        Color negatives of Graham, Humphrey and Hawkins; Hittite sculpture; corn; children, probably Camp Treetops; Barbara Morgan in turban; Beaumont Newhall; copies of letters from visual directors; copies of paintings by Annita Delano and of students work from Delano-Morgan classes at UCLA; darkroom photographs; reproductions of articles about Barbara Morgan exhibitions 1934 and 1939; Dorothy Lawton recommendation for grant; James Leonard and Lee Parsons Davis, and Philippine Penitente Islands (photographs by Willard Morgan?); and unidentified.
      - circa 1920s, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 555, Folders 1-4)
        Adobe House and Brick Making Imperial Valley, Burbank Firemen and Archery, Boy Scouts, Reproductions from Books, Braille, Barbara works, La Brea Tar Pits, Dolls, Dog sled pictures.
      - undated, Negatives (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 556, Folders 1-7)
        World War II and Nazi subjects by John Heartfield and photomontage by Alfredo Valente.
      - circa 1925-1938, undated, Negatives (35mm and 4 x 5), and copy negatives (8 x 10 and 4 x 5) from reproduction files. (Box 558, Folders 1-21)
        Dance photographs of Martha Graham and Group 1938 in Indian American Document, Bennington: Graham and Hawkins, Louis Horst, and Primitive Mysteries. Also includes negatives of Barbara Morgan exhibitions and copy negatives of photographs shown in exhibitions.
        Also includes 35mm negatives of Sabro Hasagawa, copy negatives of Barbara Morgan experimental and dance photographs, copy negatives of Edward Weston photographs, and copies of Otis Art Institute students' works.
      - 1954, 1965, undated, Negatives (35mm and 2-1/4 inch) (Box 559)
        Morgan family: Lloyd, Janet, very young Nils, Caitlin, Lael, Adele and Eric, pond construction, Franklin Falls, waterskiing, graduations, fishing; and Papago Reservation 1954 Arizona. Also includes negatives by Barbara Morgan of Douglas Morgan and a trip the two took together to Mesa Verde following Douglas's graduation from Colorado College, undated.
        Some of the negatives in this box correspond with prints in Box 154.
      - 1940-1945, undated, Negatives and contact prints (5 x 7 and smaller) (Box 560)
        Barbara Morgan La Danza Moderna exhibit at MOMA 1940 or 1945 (5 x 7 and smaller negatives and contact prints).
        Summer's Children and camps: Camp Fresh Air, Camps Anita and Bliss, Pioneer-Sketch. (35mm, 2-/4" and 4 x 5 negatives). Some of the camp negatives correspond to prints in Box 430.
        Southwest: Barbara Morgan painting in Grand Canyon and possibly Mono Lake, and Willard Morgan atop Rainbow Bridge.
        Unidentified and attributed to other photographers: Unidentified negs of man and woman inside a house, 3 x 4" negative of a crane, and a small print (2-3/8" x 4") marked "Copyright 1933 by Chas. M. Brown / Mt. Dora, New Mexico / The great meteor Mar. 24, 33". Also includes negatives of political cartoons sent to Willard Morgan.
    - Cut film (4 x 5 format and smaller), 1920s-1970s, undated
      - 1938-1939, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 290)
        Martha Graham and Group in rehearsals and demonstrations of the work American Document choreographed by Martha Graham in the Graham Studio NYC and at Bennington College.
        Also includes non-dance photographs of Graham and Eric Hawkins at Bennington College, and Erick Hawkins Striding Figure, 1939.
      - 1935-1945, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 291)
        Martha Graham and Group in rehearsals and studio photography sessions for works choreographed by Martha Graham including American Document, American Provincials, Chronicle, Columbiad (Graham solo), Deaths and Entrances. Dancers include Martha Graham, Erick Hawkins, Sophie Maslow, Frieda Flier, Jean Erdman, Jane Dudley, and other dancers in the Martha Graham Company.
      - 1934-1945, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 292)
        Martha Graham and Group in rehearsals and studio photography sessions for works choreographed by Martha Graham including Deaths and Entrances, Deep Song, Ekstasis, El Penitente, and Every Soul is a Circus. Dancers include Martha Graham, Erick Hawkins, Merce Cunningham and other dancers in the Martha Graham Company.
      - 1935-1940, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 293)
        Martha Graham and Group in rehearsals and studio photography sessions for works choreographed by Martha Graham including every Soul is a Circus and Frontier. Most of the photographs in this box depict dancers Martha Graham, Erick Hawkins and Merce Cunningham. Some photographs also include other Graham dancers.
        Also includes contact prints with image dimensions 2-3/8" x 2-5/8" (60mm x 70mm).
      - 1935-1940, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 294)
        Martha Graham and Erick Hawkins in rehearsals and studio photography sessions for works choreographed by Martha Graham including Frontier, Harlequinade, Imperial Gesture, Immediate Tragedy, Lamentation, and Letter to the World. Most of the photographs in this box are of Martha Graham alone. Letter to the World photographs also include Erick Hawkins.
      - 1931-1941, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 295)
        Martha Graham and Group in rehearsals and studio photography sessions for works choreographed by Martha Graham including Letter to the World, Primitive Canticles, Primitive Mysteries, and Punch and Judy. Dancers included are Martha Graham, Erick Hawkins, Merce Cunningham, with some ensemble photographs of Martha Graham and Group.
      - circa 1894-1941, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 296)
        Martha Graham and Group in rehearsals and studio photography sessions for works choreographed by Martha Graham including Punch and Judy (dancers Martha Graham, Erick Hawkins, Jean Erdman, Jane Dudley and Ethel Butler), Sarabande, Satyric Festival, and War Theme; 1935 portraits of Martha Graham; Graham technique demonstrated by Graham dancers Dorothy Bird, May O'Donnell, Ethel Butler, and Nina Caiserman.
        Also includes early photographs of Martha Graham not taken by Barbara Morgan--baby, early dancer (in St. Denis costumes) and family; and photographs of Martha Graham's signature.
      - circa 1938, undated, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 297)
        Martha Graham dancers (Merce Cunningham, Jean Erdman, some group, and some unidentified Graham dancers) demonstrating Graham technique; and Martha Graham with Erick Hawkins. Also includes 2" x 3" prints of Martha Graham in unidentified dance.
      - 1938-1944, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 298)
        Dancers Thelma Babbitz, Bill Bales in Green Mountain Boy and Adios, Valerie Bettis in Prairie Born, Desperate Heart, Al Bezar, Miriam Blecher, Katherine Bolland, Si Lan Chen, Merce Cunningham in Totem Ancestor.
      - 1941-1944, undated, Contact prints (4 x 5) (Box 299)